<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Documenting the Lule Sámi lexicon files</title>

    <authors>
      <person email="trond.trosterud@hum.uit.no" name="Trond Trosterud" />
    </authors>
  </header>

  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <p>This file describes the Lule Sami lexicon files. The documentation is
      not complete. Status quo for the lexicon files is as follows
      (030310):</p>

      <ul>
        <li>The inflection is more or less covered, with the following
        exceptions: <ul>
            <li>Comparative and attributive forms of adjectives</li>

            <li>Numerals are missing</li>

            <li>There are minor holes in the morphology here and there:<ul>
                <li>Verbs: Present participle is missing (I-III CG must be
                fixed)</li>
              </ul></li>
          </ul></li>

        <li>The derivation is not covered.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>The file structure for the lexicon files is the same as for the other
      Sami lgs, cf. the <a href="../sme/docu-sme-flowchart.html">Northern Sámi
      flowchart</a>.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The Nouns</title>

      <p>The nouns are divided in the following sublexica (the
      noun-smj-lex.txt file is organized in chapters according to these
      sublexica).</p>

      <source>Spiik    LEXICON      Type
--------------------------------------------------------------
even     MUORRA       2syll stem with cg (note Q1)
even     NOADE        2syll stem without cg (note missing Q1)
even     KINO         2syll stem without any morphophonology
even 4sl GÅNÅGIS      4syll stem with cg
even 4sl CELSIUS      4syll stem without cg
odd      ÅRES         oddsyll, cg, C-final, 2ndsyll vowchange
odd      GÁMAS        oddsyll, cg, C-final, no 2ndsyll vowchange
odd      GAHPER       oddsyll, no cg, no vowchange
odd      BENA         oddsyll, cg, vowchange, V-final nominative
cntr     SARVES       cntr C-final with cg
cntr     SUOLOJ
cntr     GUOMOJ       III-I cg
</source>

      <p>NB! Note that grade III nouns of the biel'lo type must be added as
      such in the lexicon, in order not to get wrong CG results. Also,
      non-gradating nouns must go to different sublexica, and these lexica
      must point to CG-free case sublexica.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The Adjectives</title>

      <p>The adjective lexica follow Spiik's numbering system, in the
      following way: /</p>

      <p></p>

      <source>Spiik   LEXICON      Type
--------------------------------------------------------------------
even 1a GIEVRRA      Attr WeG, -s
even 1b NUORRA       Attr =
even 1c HÁVSSKE      Attr w/o WeG, -s
even 1d UNNE         Attr e &gt; a~e, WeG
even 2  ÁRMMOGIS     Attr = Pred. Nom. Sg.
misc.   ASIDASJ
misc.   TJALMEDIBME
odd a.  TJIEGOS      Adj. on -k, negating on -dahkes, sm adjs on -os
odd b.  BASSTEL      Adj. on -et, -l, -r
odd c.  MUTTÁK       Adj. on -ák, &nbsp;{aáå}s, Attr -is or ==
odd d.  ALLAK        Adj. on -ak, Attr on -a
odd e.  GALMAS       Adj. on WeG -as, Attr on StrG -a
---------------------------------------------------------------------
</source>

      <section>
        <title>The Attribute</title>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>The case forms</title>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Comparative and superlative</title>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The verbs</title>

      <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>

        <p>Auxiliary verbs and main verbs are treated separately. . Note the
        concatenated entries for auxiliary + negation.</p>

        <p>The main verbs are divided in even (-at, -åt, -ot, -et), odd (-it)
        and contracted (-át, -åt~ut, -it) stems.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>The auxiliaries</title>

        <p>The auxiliaries have the lexica NEG, ÅRROT, LIEHKET. The verb stems
        are declared initially in the <code>verb-smj.txt</code> file, and the
        continuation lexica themselves are declared towards the end of the
        <code>smj-lex.txt</code> file. Since the auxiliaries are irregular,
        the suffixes are just listed.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>The main verbs</title>

        <section>
          <title>The disposition</title>

          <p>The disposition is as follows:</p>

          <ol>
            <li>The stem class lexica and their immediate daughter lexica<ol>
                <li>Even-syllabic stems<ol>
                    <li>Modals</li>

                    <li>Ordinary main verbs</li>
                  </ol></li>

                <li>Odd-syllabic stems</li>

                <li>Contracted stems</li>
              </ol></li>

            <li>Main inflectional categories</li>

            <li>Intermediate suffix lexica</li>

            <li>Final suffix lexica</li>

            <li>Derivation</li>
          </ol>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Inflection</title>

          <section>
            <title>The stem class lexica</title>

            <p>Each main stem type has its own section, for the lexica with
            pointers from the verb file. These lecixa first split into a
            non-derivational and a derivational part, with
            <code>BASSATStem</code> and <code>DeverbalVerbsBASSAT</code>
            (etc., for the other lexica). The latter point to the derivational
            lexica, cf. next xection. The former is a set of lexica with
            pointers towards passive (<code>EVENPASSIVE</code>) and
            non-passive (<code>BASSATINCH</code>) continuation lexica.</p>

            <p>The <code>BASSATINCH</code> etc. lexica point twice to
            <code>INFL-EVEN</code> etc., both directly and via the inchoative
            <code>-goahte-</code> suffix.</p>
          </section>

          <section>
            <title>The main inflectional categories</title>

            <p>The <code>INFL-EVEN, INFL-o-, INFL-ODD, INFL-CONTR</code>
            lexica then point to the different person-number sublexica. Note
            that there in Lule Sámi are two person-number suffix series. One
            is used in even-syllabic verbs for present tense and in
            odd-syllabic verbs for past tense, this is named with roman
            numeral I in the sublexica to follow. The other one is used in
            even-syllabic verbs for past tense and potential, lexica with this
            suffix set are named with roman numerals II. The reason for this
            abstraction is that we do not need to write the same suffixes
            several times, rather, we may refer to the same suffix set from
            different stem-tense-mode combinations.</p>

            <p>The pointers to the person-number lexica are done on blocks of
            nine and nine.</p>
          </section>

          <section>
            <title>The intermediate suffix lexica</title>

            <p>Here, the person-number blocks are split in different groups,
            according to morphophonological processes.</p>
          </section>

          <section>
            <title>The final suffix lexica</title>

            <p>At last, we are in a position to assign person-number
            suffixes.</p>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Derivation</title>

          <p>The passive lexica add the passive suffixes, and thereafter point
          further on to the inflection lexica.</p>

          <p>The derivational system takes the Northern Sámi system as a
          starting point, but does not (yet) take transitivity into account.
          The section on derivation awaits a presentation of Lule Sami
          derivational morphology, taking Kintel and Nystø/Johnsen as a
          starting point.</p>

          <p>From the stems of each stemtype, there are pointers to lexica
          <code>DeverbalVerbsBASSAT, DeverbalNounsBASSAT,
          DeverbalVerbsJÅLLÅRIT, DeverbalNounsJÅLLÅRIT, DeverbalNounsOADDÁT,
          DeverbalVerbsOADDÁT</code>. All these lexical are found in a
          separate section "Verbal derivation" following the section on verbal
          inflection. So far, only the first of these lexica has any
          continuation lexica, pointing back to the relevant verb lexica via a
          set of derivational suffixes.</p>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The closed classes</title>

      <section>
        <title>Pronouns</title>

        <section>
          <title>Personal pronouns</title>

          <p>Lule Sami personal pronouns are added to the file
          closed-smj.lex.txt. They differ from the corresponding Northern Sami
          ones in having uniform sublexica across the different persons. The
          initial lexicon <em>Personal</em> splits into nine sublexica, 3 for
          each person, each pointing to one sublexicon for each number. The 3
          number sublexica (<em>persproncasesg</em>, etc. then give the case
          forms.</p>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Demonstrative pronouns</title>

          <p>This lexicon contains both declineable and indeclineable entries.
          The declineable ones point to two sublexica, <em>demcas</em> and
          <em>dátcas</em>. Of these, the former splits into number
          sublexica.</p>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Reflexive pronouns</title>

          <p>In the <em>Reflexive</em> sublexicon, the reflexive pronoun
          <em>iesj</em> gets spelled-out forms for the Px-less nominative,
          whereas the oblique forms are directed to sublexica for sg and pl.
          There they get appropriate stems, and the singular forms are
          redirected to the ordinary nominal Px lexica. Acc PxSg1 and Gen
          PxSg1 have exceptional forms, they are listed as such.</p>

          <p>The plural reflexives do have deviating Px forms, they are listed
          in the closed-smj-lex.txt file itself, first by establishing dual
          and plural substems for each person (in the lexicon
          <em>PxCiPlstem</em>), and then by giving the personal suffixes (in
          the lexicon <em>PxCPlstem.</em>).</p>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Interrogative pronouns</title>

          <p>These are <em>mij</em> and <em>guhti</em>. The nominative and
          partitive of <em>mij</em> are given separately, as are two
          nominatives of <em>guhti</em>. Furthermore, <em>mij</em> has some
          idiosyncratic forms. The rest are generated in lexicon
          <em>oblintercas</em>.</p>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Indefinite pronouns</title>

          <p>This has not been done, the lexicon has only one entry, the
          pronoun <em>vehi</em>.</p>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Subjunctions and Conjunctions</title>

        <p>10-20 subjunctions and conjunctions are listed, and given
        appropriate tags.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Numerals</title>

        <p>All basic numerals are listed, and given appropriate case
        inflection. No attempts have been done wrt. making a numeral generator
        (for combinations of numerals, such as fivehundredandtwentyfour,
        etc.). The documentation in Spiik was not entirely clear on this point
        (are complex numeral written in one word or not, and how is the case
        inflection?) Nystø/Johnsen, on the other hand, write the numerals
        together, and the best thing to do seems to be to make a
        representation parallel to the sme one.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Particles and Interjections</title>

        <p>4-5 particles and interjections are listed, and given tags.</p>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Adverbs</title>

      <p>The file adv-smj-lex.txt contains lexical adverbs. Still missing is
      defect case paradigms, and adverbs derived from adjectives.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Adpositions</title>

      <p>The file differs between pre- and postpositions.</p>

      <p class="last_modified">Last modified $Date$, by
      $Author$</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>