<?xml version = '1.0' encoding = 'UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Documenting the Lule Sámi lexicon files</title>
    <authors>
      <person email="trond.trosterud@hum.uit.no" name="Trond Trosterud" />
    </authors>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section id="intro" >
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>This file describes the Lule Sami lexicon files. The documentation is not complete. Status quo for the lexicon files is as follows (030310):</p>
      <ul>
        <li>The inflection is covered, with the following exceptions: <ul>
            <li>Comparative and attributive forms of adjectives</li>
            <li>...</li>
          </ul>
        </li>
        <li>The derivation is not covered.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>The file structure for the lexicon files is the same as for the other Sami lgs, cf. the <a href="../sme/docu-sme-flowchart.html" >flowchart</a>.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="noun" >
      <title>The Nouns</title>
      <p>The nouns are divided in the following sublexica (the noun-smj-lex.txt file is organized in chapters according to these sublexica).</p>
      <source>Spiik    LEXICON      Type
-------------------------
even     MUORRA       2syll stem with cg (note Q1)
even     NOADE        2syll stem without cg (note missing Q1)
even     KINO         2syll stem without any morphophonology
even 4sl GÅNÅGIS      4syll stem with cg
even 4sl CELSIUS      4syll stem without cg
odd      ÅRES         oddsyll, cg, C-final, 2ndsyll vowchange
odd      GÁMAS        oddsyll, cg, C-final, no 2ndsyll vowchange
odd      GAHPER       oddsyll, no cg, no vowchange
odd      BENA         oddsyll, cg, vowchange, V-final nominative
cntr     SARVES       cntr C-final with cg
cntr     SUOLOJ       
cntr     GUOMOJ       III-I cg


</source>
      <p>NB! Note that grade III nouns of the biel'lo type must be added as such in the lexicon, in order not to get wrong CG results. Also, non-gradating nouns must go to different sublexica, and these lexica must point to CG-free case sublexica.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="adj" >
      <title>The Adjectives</title>
      <p>The adjective lexica follow Spiik's numbering system, in the following way: /</p>
      <p/>
      <source>Spiik   LEXICON      Type
--------------------------------------------------------------------
even 1a GIEVRRA      Attr WeG, -s
even 1b NUORRA       Attr =
even 1c HÁVSSKE      Attr w/o WeG, -s
even 1d UNNE         Attr e > a~e, WeG
even 2  ÁRMMOGIS     Attr = Pred. Nom. Sg.
misc.   ASIDASJ
misc.   TJALMEDIBME
odd a.  TJIEGOS      Adj. on -k, negating on -dahkes, sm adjs on -os
odd b.  BASSTEL      Adj. on -et, -l, -r
odd c.  MUTTÁK       Adj. on -ák,  {aáå}s, Attr -is or ==
odd d.  ALLAK        Adj. on -ak, Attr on -a
odd e.  GALMAS       Adj. on WeG -as, Attr on StrG -a
---------------------------------------------------------------------
</source>
      <section id="The_Attribute" >
        <title>The Attribute</title>
      </section>
      <section id="The_case_forms" >
        <title>The case forms</title>
      </section>
      <section id="Comparative_and_superlative" >
        <title>Comparative and superlative</title>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="verb" >
      <title>The Verbs</title>
      <section id="Intro" >
        <title>Intro</title>
        <p>The auxiliary verbs have been added. Note the concatenated entries for auxiliary + negation.</p>
        <p>The main verbs are divided in even (-at, -åt, -ot, -et), odd (-it) and contracted (-átm -åt~ut, -it) stems.</p>
      </section>
      <section id="Inflection" >
        <title>Inflection</title>
        <p>...</p>
      </section>
      <section id="Derivation" >
        <title>Derivation</title>
        <p>The derivational system takes the Northern Sámi system as a starting point, but does not (yet) take transitivity into account.</p>
        <source>BASSAT -> +V: BASSATStem ; +V DeverbalVerbsBASSAT ;
BASSATStem -> 
</source>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="cl" >
      <title>The closed classes</title>
      <section id="Pronouns" >
        <title>Pronouns</title>
        <section id="Personal_pronouns" >
          <title>Personal pronouns</title>
          <p>Lule Sami personal pronouns are added to the file closed-smj.lex.txt. They differ from the corresponding Northern Sami ones in having uniform sublexica across the different persons. The initial lexicon <em>Personal</em> splits into nine sublexica, 3 for each person, each pointing to one sublexicon for each number. The 3 number sublexica (<em>persproncasesg</em>, etc. then give the case forms.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="Demonstrative_pronouns" >
          <title>Demonstrative pronouns</title>
          <p>This lexicon contains both declineable and indeclineable entries. The declineable ones point to two sublexica, <em>demcas</em> and <em>dátcas</em>. Of these, the former splits into number sublexica.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="Reflexive_pronouns" >
          <title>Reflexive pronouns</title>
          <p>In the <em>Reflexive</em> sublexicon, the reflexive pronoun <em>iesj</em> gets spelled-out forms for the Px-less nominative, whereas the oblique forms are directed to sublexica for sg and pl. There they get appropriate stems, and the singular forms are redirected to the ordinary nominal Px lexica. Acc PxSg1 and Gen PxSg1 have exceptional forms, they are listed as such.</p>
          <p>The plural reflexives do have deviating Px forms, they are listed in the closed-smj-lex.txt file itself, first by establishing dual and plural substems for each person (in lexicon <em>PxCiPlstem</em>), and then by giving the personal suffixes (in lexicon <em>PxCPlstem</em>
          </p>
        </section>
        <section id="Interrogative_pronouns" >
          <title>Interrogative pronouns</title>
          <p>These are <em>mij</em> and <em>guhti</em>. The nominative and partitive of <em>mij</em> are given separately, as are two nominatives of <em>guhti</em>. Furthermore, <em>mij</em> has some idiosyncratic forms. The rest are generated in lexicon <em>oblintercas</em>.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="Indefinite_pronouns" >
          <title>Indefinite pronouns</title>
          <p>This has not been done, the lexicon has only one entry, the pronoun <em>vehi</em>.</p>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section id="Subjunctions_and_Conjunctions" >
        <title>Subjunctions and Conjunctions</title>
        <p>10-20 subjunctions and conjunctions are listed, and given appropriate tags.</p>
      </section>
      <section id="Numerals" >
        <title>Numerals</title>
        <p>All basic numerals are listed, and given appropriate case inflection. No attempts have been done wrt. making a numeral generator (for combinations of numerals, such as fivehundredandtwentyfour, etc.). The documentation in Spiik was not entirely clear on this point (are complex numeral written in one word or not, and how is the case inflection?)</p>
      </section>
      <section id="Particles_and_Interjections" >
        <title>Particles and Interjections</title>
        <p>4-5 particles and interjections are listed, and given tags.</p>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="adv" >
      <title>Adverbs</title>
      <p>The file adv-smj-lex.txt contains lexical adverbs. Still missing is defect case paradigms, and adverbs derived from adjectives.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="ad" >
      <title>Adpositions</title>
      <p>The file differs between pre- and postpositions.</p>
      <p class="last_modified">Last modified $Date$, by $Author$</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
