<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title></title>

    <authors>
      <person email="trond.trosterud@hum.uit.no" name="Trond Trosterud" />
    </authors>
  </header>

  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Preprocessing the input</title>

      <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Tokenizing</title>

        <section>
          <title>Obsolete: The tokenizer file tok.txt</title>

          <p>Just as for Northern Sámi, the Lule Sámi preprocessing was
          earlier done with the Xerox <em>tokenize</em> tool and the
          language-specific file tok.txt. The code itself is written as a set
          of regular expressions, and the source file (tok.txt) was compiled
          by xfst. As explained for the sme preprocessing, this approach was
          replaced by a preprocessor script, written in perl,
          <code>gt/script/preprocess</code>. </p>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>The current preprocessor</title>

          <p>Preprocessing is done by the perl script
          <code>gt/script/preprocess</code>, which is language-independent.
          The script is documented <a
          href="../../ling/preprocessor.html">here</a>. The language dependent
          part of the script shall be done via a </p>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Handling abbreviations</title>

          <fixme author="Trond, Tomi, Saara">We need Lule Sami abbreviations,
          and the Makefile routine for generating the abbr.txt file.</fixme>

          <p>On the other hand side, as long as we have neither lexicon nor
          texts for Lule Sámi, we have no need for a Lule Sámi preprocessor
          either.</p>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Spell relaxation of æ/ä, ø/ö</title>

        <p>This is a feature common to Lule and Southern Sami, not to be found
        in Northern Sami. The letter æ/ä and ø/ö are used interchangeably in
        Norway and Sweden. The parser should thus accept any version of
        them.</p>

        <p>The xfst file to handle this is short, it consists of one line:</p>

        <source>ń (-&gt;) ñ, ŋ (-&gt;) ñ, æ (-&gt;) ä, ø (-&gt;) ö ;</source>

        <p>The line says that æ may optionally be replaced by ä and that ø may
        optionally be replaced with ö, and the same for the different ways of
        writing ŋ. A problem with this script is that it does not work,
        although it worked earlier in 2005.</p>

        <fixme author="Trond, Tomi, Saara">Fix the spellrelax.regex
        script</fixme>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Initial capitalization</title>

        <p>This works like the Northern Sami file, cf. <a
        href="../sme/docu-sme-preprocessor.html#ini">the documentation for
        Northern Sami initial capitalization</a>. The content of the file is
        slightly different, since the letter repertoire is different as
        well.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Capitalization of whole words</title>

        <p>This has not yet been implemented.</p>
      </section>

      <p class="last_modified">Last modified $Date$, by
      $Author$</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>