<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document xml:lang="en">
  <header>
    <title>A list of open normativity issues</title>

    <authors>
      <person email="thomas.omma@samediggi.no" name="Thomas Omma" />

      <person email="trond.trosterud@hum.uit.no" name="Trond Trosterud" />
    </authors>
  </header>

  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Background</title>

      <p>The immediate background for this list is the meeting of the Lule
      Sámi language board meeting. The list will be relevant also after this
      meeting, though. It is a key document to the normativity issued faced by
      the sámi spellchecker program, and lists open normativity issues.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Even and contracted stemtypes in nom. and gen./acc. when joined
      with pos. suffix</title>

      <p>The normative grammars are far from precise in this issue with
      respect to stem-vowel change and central consonant gradation in each
      case.</p>

      <p>Status/actions:</p>

      <ol>
        <li>Fully described with examples</li>

        <li>Sent to Giellalávdegoddi</li>

        <li>...</li>

        <li>…</li>
      </ol>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Loan word intergration</title>

      <p>What policy should be followed here? There are no normative decisions
      made. The writers of Sámásta say that principles have been developed
      over time, but the practice is unstable and there seems to be a whole
      lot of confusion (s. 272 ff.). The book gives some suggestions of how to
      incorporate loanwords, but there hasn't obviously been any normative
      organ involved.</p>

      <p>Status/actions:</p>

      <ol>
        <li>Fully described with examples</li>

        <li>Sent to Giellalávdegoddi</li>

        <li>...</li>

        <li>...</li>
      </ol>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Dialect spesiffic forms</title>

      <p>According to two main sources there are different ways of writing the
      same word in Sweden an Norway. F.exs "luohttedahtte" and "kasus" in
      Sweden and "luohtedahtte" and "káus" in Norway. We have added both
      forms, but this gives us some problems. If someone in Norway writes
      "luohttedahtte", the speller doesn't mark it as red, even though the
      usual form in Norway is "luohtedahtte". The same problem in Sweden, only
      opposite. This meens that the speller doesn't correct words that are
      written diffrently in Sweden and Norway, even though it's "wrong" .</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Short froms</title>

      <p>Some words are beeing shortened f eks: riek (riekta)and guok(guokta).
      "Tjuohte" is also beeing shortened into "tjuot", in compounds. To some
      degree we can find these words beeing used in dictionaries and grammars.
      Is it allowed to use these shortened forms in writing? </p>
    </section>

    <p class="last_modified">Last modified: $Date$, by
    $Author$</p>
  </body>
</document>